Finding Aid for Samuel T. Dana papers 1893-1970
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Samuel T. Dana papers 1893-1970 1925-1968
Dana, Samuel Trask, 1883-1978
851592 Aa 2, UAm
Professor of forestry and forest economics and first dean of the School of Forestry at the University of Michigan, prominent conservationist, chairman of the U.S. Timber Conservation Boards in the 1930s and president of the Society of American Foresters. Records including correspondence and topical files, primarily document his participation in conservation organizations and professional associations and service on government boards and commissions. There is some material on his scholarly and administrative work at the University of Michigan, but the latter is more fully documented in the records of the University of Michigan School of Natural Resources.
9 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Samuel T. Dana and came to the library in several accession, 1968-1971. Donor no. 2467
The collection is open for research.
Samuel T. Dana, a specialist in forestry and forest economics, was the first dean of the University of Michigan School of Natural Resources, serving from 1927 to 1951. Born April 21, 1883 in Portland, Maine, Dana was educated at Bowdoin College (1904) and Yale University (1907). He immediately entered the U.S. Forest Service upon graduation where he first engaged in investigations of the culture of white pine and paper birch forests. He later helped to establish several forest experiment stations and conducted further research on the economic value of forests.
During World War I, Dana was a U.S. Army captain in charge of lumber statistics, serving as secretary of the commodity committee on lumber from 1918 to 1919. After the war he returned to the U.S. Forest Service as a forest economist and then was appointed forest commissioner of Maine where he served from 1921 to 1923 and where he was in charge of forest fire control. From 1923 to 1927, Dana was director of the Northeastern Forest Experiment Station of the U.S. Forest Service. He served there until coming to the University of Michigan.
Dana was active in his profession and as a teacher. During the 1930s, he was chairman of the U.S. Timber Conservation Boards. He also served as president of the Society of American Foresters and was editor in chief of its Journal of Forestry. From 1948 to 1949, he also served on the Hoover Commission charged with the reorganization of the executive branch of the government. In 1958, President Eisenhower appointed him to served on the National Outdoor Recreation Review Commission which studied trends in population, transportation and recreational land uses. He also served on the National Citizens Committee for Outdoor Recreation, and was selected by the Society of American Foresters to study different proposals to preserve California's redwood trees.
Dana died May 8, 1978
The Dana collection has been arranged into three series: Correspondence, Topical Files, and Photographs.
The files document Dana's professional activities mainly from the period after his World War I service and concern his organizational involvements and his participation in forestry conservation projects. Dana's role as dean of the University of Michigan School of Natural Resources is less fully documented here as these materials were retained as part of that school's record group (also housed at the Bentley Historical Library).
Subjects:
American Forestry Association.; Conservation of natural resources--United States.; Dana, Samuel Trask, 1883-1978; Forests and forestry--United States.; Mid-Century Conference on Resources for the Future (Washington, D.C.: 1953); National Popular Government League.; Society of American Foresters.; United States. Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government (1953-1955); United States. Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission.; United States. Timber Conservation Board.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Dana, Samuel Trask, 1883-1978; Forest rangers--New Mexico.; Forests--Michigan.; Lumber industry--Michigan.; Pinchot Institute for Conservation Studies.
Contributors:
Baxter, Percival Proctor, 1876-1969; Brower, David, 1912-2000; Chapman, Herman Haupt, 1874-1963.; Clapp, Earle H. (Earle Hart), 1877-1970; Clepper, Henry Edward, 1901-1987.; Cohen, Wilbur J. (Wilbur Joseph), 1913-1987.; Conservation Foundation.; Crafts, Edward C. (Edward Clayton), 1910-; Craig, James B.; Fritz, Emanuel, 1886-; Graves, Henry Solon, 1871-1951.; Greeley, William Buckhout, 1879-1955.; Hosmer, Ralph Sheldon, 1874-1963.; Johnston, Don Porter, 1884-; Krueger, Myron.; McArdle, Richard E. (Richard Edwin), 1899-1983; Metcalf, Woodbridge, 1888-; Moore, Barrington, 1913-2005; Nelson, DeWitt, 1901-; Pack, Charles Lathrop, 1857-1937.; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946.; Pomeroy, Kenneth Brownridge, 1907-; Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman.; Roosevelt, Nicholas, 1893-1982; Sargent, Francis.; Save-the-Redwoods League.; Schmitz, Henry, 1892-1965.; Sierra Club.; Taft, Charles P. (Charles Phelps), 1897-1983; Train, Russell E., 1920-2012; Udall, Stewart L.; Vaux, Henry J. (Henry James), 1912-2000; Zon, Raphael, 1874-1956.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series dates primarily from the mid-1920s to 1968. Dana's correspondents are other professionals in the field of forestry. A selective list of correspondents is attached to this finding aid. The series is arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence 1918, 1921-1957, 32 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1958-April 1966, 27 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence May 1966-1970, 8 folders (Box 3)
- Topical File
  Topical Files is the series that brings together into an alphabetical arrangement Dana's records from his participation in professional organizations, government commissions, and special project groups. The largest portions of this series concern the Hoover Commission, the National Popular Government League, the Outdoor Recreation Review Commission, the Society of American Foresters, and the Timber Conservation Board.
  - American Forestry Association 1952-1966, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Battelle Memorial Institute 1963-1965, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - California Land Ownership Study 1956-1959, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Conservation Library Center 1961-1967, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Dana-Personal
    - 1893-1904 (Box 3)
    - 1917-1936 (Box 3)
    - 1949-1966 (Box 3)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica article 1958-1968 (Box 3)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica article 1967 (Box 3)
  - Forest History Society 1965-1967 (Box 3)
  - Higgins Lake conferences 1952-1953, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Hoover Commission undated, 1947-1957, 19 folders (Box 4)
  - Lumber Code 1933-1934, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Mid-Century Conference on Resources for the Future 1953, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Minnesota land study 1961 (Box 5)
  - Minnesota Natural Resources Council 1961-1963 (Box 5)
  - Miscellanea 1931-1968, 11 folders (Box 5)
  - National Association of Manufacturers-Native Land 1955-1958 (Box 5)
  - National Popular Government League 1927-1939, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - National Popular Government League 1940-1953, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission
    - Papers 1957-1965, 22 folders (Box 6)
    - Selection of research director 1959-1960 (Box 7)
    - Selection of executive secretary 1958-1959 (Box 7)
    - Report 1962, 2 parts (Box 7)
    - Progress report 1961 (Box 7)
    - Project authorization 1959 (Box 7)
    - Summaries of Study Reports 1961, 2 parts (Box 7)
    - Advisory Council meetings 1959-1961, 5 volumes (Box 7)
    - Meetings of the Commission October 1959-August 1960, 6 volumes (Box 7)
    - Meetings of the Commission December 1960-July 1961, 7 volumes (Box 8)
  - Pinchot Institute for Conservation Studies 1964, 1966-1968, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Redwoods National Park undated, 1964-1968, 8 folders (Box 8)
  - Society of American Foresters 1932-1968, 8 folders (Box 9)
  - Speeches and articles 1905-1924, 1953-1960, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Stearns case 1954-1955, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Timber Conservation Board 1931-1932, 5 folders (Box 9)
  - Yale Forestry School 1911-1965, 4 folders (Box 9)
    (scattered dates)
- Photographs
  The Photograph series consists of two folders, including portraits of Dana, photos of Dana and other members of the Pinchot Institute for Conservation Studies, and collected copyprints of historical images of Michigan lumbering.
  - Copyprints of historical logging photographs taken from the records of the Michigan Department of Conservation (Box 9)
  - Portraits of STD; meetings of Pinchot Institute for Conservation (Box 9)
Selective List of Correspondents
Baxter, Percival Proctor, 1876-
1921
Brower, David Ross, 1912-
1960-1961
Chapman, Herman Haupt, 1874-1963.
April 29, 1929, November 10 and 16, 1934, 1936, August 20, 1942, 1944-1945, June 9, 1948, January 22, 1952, 1953, February 18, 1959
Clapp, Earle Hart, 1877-
1926, 1935, 1942
Clepper, Henry Edward, 1901-
June 29, 1948, 1949, January 6, 1950, March 12, 1956, September 14, 1964, 1965
Cohen, Wilbur Joseph, 1913-
1961
Conservation Foundation
1960-1967
Crafts, Edward Clayton, 1910-
1957, February 2, 1965, April 20, 1960, December 3, 1968, 1969
Craig, James B.
1955-1959, 1963, 1965
Fritz, Emanuel
1930, April 17, 1946, 1948, November 17, 1953, October 23, 1957, February 19, 1958, May 26, 1961, February 3, 1964, May 7, 1965, March 3, 1966
Graves, Henry Solon, 1871-1951.
1918, 1921, March 23, 1925
Greeley, William B., 1879-1955.
1921, 1925, 1926, 1927, 1951, 1952, May 26, 1953, January 21, 1954
Hosmer, Ralph Sheldon, 1874-1963.
1922-1925, 1926, 1929, 1930, 1953, September 4, 1955, 1958, 1961
Johnston, Don Porter, 1884-
October 8, 1951, 1952, 1953
Krueger, Myron
1956-1958, 1960, March 24, 1961, 1962, April 25, 1963, May 7, 1965, 1966, 1967
McArdle, Richard Edwin, 1899-
1952, September 28, 1954, 1955, September 6, 1964, 1965, 1966, April 14, 1967, February 3, 1968
Metcalf, Woodbridge, 1888-
October 17, 1926, November 15, 1926, August 3, 1958, July 1, 1968
Moore, Barrington
1923, 1925, 1928, November 23, 1943, March 9, 1946
Nelson, DeWitt, 1901-
1957, 1958, 1965
Pack, Charles Lathrop, 1857-1937.
1926
Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946.
March 8, 1921, October 29 and 31, 1945
Pomeroy, Kenneth Brownridge, 1907-
1963-1967
Rockefeller, Laurance S., 1910-
September 18, 1957, 1959, 1960, November 9 and 22, 1961, April 3, 1962
Roosevelt, Nicholas, 1893-
July 23 and 28, 1959, August 14, 1959
Sargent, Francis
1959-1961
Save-the-Redwoods League
1965, 1966, 1968
Schmitz, Henry, 1892-1965.
1942, 1945
Sierra Club
1960, 1961, 1965
Taft, Charles Phelps, 1897-
1955
Train, Russell Errol, 1920-
1965-1967
Udall, Stewart Lee, 1920-
1962
Vaux, Henry James, 1912-
1950s and 1960s
Zon, Raphael, 1874-1956.
April 14, 1921, July 1, 1921, May 22, 28, and 31, 1923, May 4, 1943